Okay בוקר טוב boker tov everybody גמר חתימה טובה. gmar chatima tova.
Should be a meaningful fast and דאווענינג davening on יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, a meaningful יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. And we pick up on
the bottom of עין גמל עמוד ב. ayin gimel amud bet. Today's
דף daf is עין דלת. ayin dalet. We pick up at the
bottom of עין גמל עמוד ב. ayin gimel amud bet.
And we have the following: ואלו הן חייבי כריתות. Ve'eilu hein chayavei
kritot. We're still dealing with what are the types of cases of
somebody who's about to be raped or whatever to force sexually to
have sexual intercourse and that you would protect her with the life
of the would-be of the would-be perpetrator of the would-be rapist. And
so it includes as we said, it's not every act of rape,
it's only those that the type of the sin are deserving of
the death penalty or כרת. karet.
And that now the גמרא Gemara sort of and the emphasis of
פגם pgam of protecting the women from being spoiled as it were,
which also has like a you know, it's not just the physical
act of rape. And now the גמרא Gemara picks up about eight
lines from the bottom. ואלו הן חייבי כריתות. Ve'eilu hein chayavei kritot.
So it includes all cases that you're an act of of intercourse
that it's of that it would be a transgression of
כרת. karet. ורמינהו, U'reminhu, I'll ask you on this. ואלו נערות שיש
להן קנס, Ve'eilu naarot sheyeish lahen knas, the following נערות, naarot, the
following maiden to have קנס, knas, you know, in a case where
they are seduced or raped, I mean not seduced, whatever, raped that
that you pay a fine if they're not married. הבא על אחותו,
Haba al achoto, so right that's the case of the תורה Torah
where if a man sort of you know rapes a girl and
she's not married, then he pays a fine, he has to be
married to her. And the point of this משנה Mishnah is is
that even though he has an obligation to marry her, there will
be some cases where he's not allowed to marry her, like if
it's his sister, right, it's one of the עריות. arayot. And even
though he's not allowed to marry her, nevertheless he still have to
pay the קנס. knas. Okay, but the משנה Mishnah goes on, if
it was a חייב מיתה chayav mita like a case, then then
he would not pay the קנס knas because we would say קם
ליה בדרבה מיניה. kam lei bid'raba minei. He was doing an act
that was deserving of the death penalty and that would override and
there would not be a קנס. knas. But if it was a
חייב כרת, chayav karet, it would be a קנס. knas. So now
the גמרא Gemara has a question because if in this guy in
this act of going to rape this girl, okay, he would what
do you call it, we could kill him, then like we saw
before in the case of the מחתרת, machteret, he would not be
liable for any monetary obligations that were incurred during the performance of
this act. It's a type of a קם ליה. kam lei. So
when we had it by מחתרת, machteret, we raised the issue, right?
Does that mean that it's a type of an act of בית
דין beis din that we're executing him or no, we're just saving
the victim, but nevertheless because his life could be taken, he does
not incur any any financial penalty. So that's what we're saying. So
why wouldn't we say, why don't we say the same thing here?
He's going to do this act of חייב כרת, chayav karet, it's
this rape of this young girl, so he shouldn't incur the קנס.
knas. So the גמרא Gemara says: אמרו רבנן קמי דרב חסדא, amru
rabanan kamei d'Rav Chisda, the rabbis said this before רב חסדא Rav
Chisda and said the following answer: משעת העראה דפגמה אשתרי מקטלא. mishat
ha'ara d'pgama ishtarei mikatla. Here's why he still pays the קנס. knas.
From the moment that he begins the penetration, העראה ha'ara is when
the sort of the crown of the penis penetrates that at that
moment he has been פוגם pogem her, he has you know spoiled
her, defiled her. And therefore after that initial moment, right, that we
can no longer kill him in the middle of the act, because
this is again the very sort of sad part about this, we're
not just protecting this girl from rape, we're protecting her from becoming
spoiled goods. Right? So the גמרא Gemara for example the point brought
before that she had already had intercourse with another male, we wouldn't
intervene in this case. So here with this very man that is
raping her, as soon as the intercourse begins, she now became spoiled
goods. And now we can't intervene even though he's continuing to rape
her. It's really horrific, you know, in terms of our modern sensibilities.
There he is continuing to rape her, we can't do anything because
in the beginning because she's already been spoiled. So therefore as soon
as he penetrates her, she's already נספגמה nispgama and we can't and
we can't kill him anymore.
אשתרי מקטלא, ishtarei mikatla, so after that moment we're no longer able
to kill him. Okay, ממונא לא משלם עד גמר ביאה mamona lo
mishalem ad gmar bia and he's not obligated to pay the money
until he finishes the act of intercourse. Now why does this קנס
knas not come until the end? So רש"י Rashi says this קנס
knas doesn't come until the end because the קנס knas was for
you know, she was a virgin, he made her a non-virgin, and
being able to rupture the hymen only comes at the end of
the act of intercourse, not at the beginning of the penetration. תוספות
Tosafot says that's not true, that's not what the fine is for,
it doesn't have to rupture the hymen or anything. So תוספות Tosafot
says the reason is is he really would be obligated in the
fine at the very beginning of the penetration. But he's not because
of קם ליה. kam lei. He's not because at the very beginning
of penetration we could kill him. So in a normal case at
that first second he would be חייב chayav in the fine, but
in this case at that first second he doesn't get the fine
because we could kill him. After that first second, we can't kill
him anymore and that's when the obligation of the fine comes in.
So that's how come you can be paying a fine in this
case. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says one minute. הניחא למאן דאמר,
Hani l'man de'amar, that's good according to the one that says העראה
זו נשיקה, ha'ara zo nishika, that העראה ha'ara is נשיקה, nishika, that
העראה ha'ara is the beginning of the act of intercourse, it's just
I said the beginning of penetration cause I was actually going to
the הלכה, halacha, but the there's an opinion that says it's just
the kissing of the genitals, meaning even an exterior, even before penetration.
Okay, so then we could understand that there's two stages. אלא למאן
דאמר העראה זו הכנסת העטרה מה איכא למימר? Ela l'man de'amar ha'ara
zo hachnasat hatara, mai ika l'meimar? But if העראה ha'ara is actually
the entering in of the crown of the penis and the penetrating,
what can you say? Why does that make it more difficult? Because,
let me just check רש"י... Rashi...
Oh, yes, because רש"י Rashi says, one minute... Right,
because רש"י Rashi says that after the beginning of the entering of
of the crown, we actually assume that she's no longer a בתולה.
besulah. So if at that initial moment, if like the, you know,
the פגם pegam happened at the moment of the genitals touched, then
you could say that the fine is incurred at the moment of
penetration. But if the פגם pegam only happened at the moment of
penetration, and we could still be have killed him at that moment,
well, after that moment, she's no longer considered to be a בתולה.
besulah. And once she's no longer considered to be a בתולה, besulah,
there's no longer a fine. The fine is only when she's a
בתולה. besulah. So you understand? What we have to do is we
have to separate the moment when we could execute him and when
she's נפגם nifgam from the moment she's not a בתולה. besulah. And
then we could say that the first moment he's liable the death
penalty, the second moment you pay the fine. So if the first
moment was the touching of the genitals, then that's נפגם nifgam and
we could've killed him, and then afterwards at the moment of penetration
we can't kill him anymore and you pay the fine. But if
the idea that he's that she's נפגם nifgam and it's an act
of ביאה bi'ah or whatever is only when the when the penetration
begins, so at that moment we can kill him and at that
moment he's liable the fine, and afterwards he's not liable the fine
cause she's no longer a בתולה. besulah. So we don't have this
case. So what's going to be the case that he's going to
have to pay the קנס? knas? So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא
אמר רב חסדא כגון שבא עליה שלא כדרכה וחזר ובא עליה כדרכה.
ela amar Rav Chisda, kegon sheba aleha shelo kedarka, vechazar uba aleha
kedarka.
Here's the case. The first act when he was raping her was
when it was anal intercourse. And therefore, there's not yet a and
therefore, that doesn't stop her from being a בתולה. besulah. Only vaginal
intercourse, which could rupture the the hymen, stops her from being a
בתולה. besulah. So the anal intercourse act, we could kill him. Okay?
But and then afterwards, she's already נפגם. nifgam. So now he's continuing
to rape her and we can't kill him cause she's already נפגם,
nifgam, and now he does the vaginal intercourse and now he pays
the fine. And at that moment, before as as he was doing
the vaginal intercourse, she was still a בתולה. besulah. Okay? So that's
one answer. Another answer. רבא אמר במנכסא שלא יהרגנה ורבי יהודה היא.
Rava amar, b'minchasa shelo yargenu v'Rabbi Yehuda hi.
The case is that the woman is saying, don't kill him, I'm
afraid he's going to kill me, leave him alone. And in that
case, the and it's going like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says once the woman says that and her life isn't
at risk, we can't intervene. Cause that's what we said at the
end of the day yesterday. For רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda we're not
just intervening to protect her from being raped or from being נפגם,
nifgam, we're intervening because her life is at risk. So as soon
as she says, I don't want him to give up my life,
I don't don't kill him so he won't kill me, oh, if
her life isn't at risk, we can't intervene. So since we can't
intervene, we're not going to say קים ליה, kimlei, because we're not
allowed to kill him. So that's why he'll pay the קנס. knas.
Okay? רב פפא אמר במפותה ודברי הכל. Rav Pappa amar, b'mefuta v'divrei
hakol. Okay? So רב פפא Rav Pappa says, okay,
that this is obviously the easiest answer, she's not being raped. Okay?
She's being seduced. So the תורה Torah has the idea of paying
a fine whether the man is raping the woman, you know, I
sort of was saying both at the beginning, wanted to separate it.
Whether the man is raping the woman, which is what we assumed,
but actually even if he seduced her, there still is going to
be a fine. But there's not going to be we can't kill
him. We'll only kill in a case where he's forcing, not when
she's agreeing, when she's a victim. If she's agreeing, she's not a
victim. Okay? So that's what he says. She's been seduced, she's not
a minor הלכתית, halachically, she's twelve years old, okay? And therefore she's
not a victim and therefore we can't kill him and therefore there's
the fine. אביי אמר ביכול להצילו באחד מאבריו רבי יונתן בן שאול
היא. Abbaye amar, b'yakhol l'hatzilo b'echad me'evarav, Rabbi Yonatan ben Shaul hi.
No,
it's a case where, here's why we can't kill here's why he
pays the fine and why we can't kill him. Not because she's
being seduced, but because we could have intervened and stopped him without
having without using lethal force. We could've stopped him with one of
his limbs, like
רבי יונתן בן שאול. Rabbi Yonatan ben Shaul. דתניא רבי יונתן בן
שאול אומר רודף שהיה רודף אחר חבירו להורגו, D'tanya, R' Yonatan ben
Shaul omer, rodeph shehaya rodeph achar chaveiro l'horgo, somebody who's running after
somebody to kill him, ויכול להצילו באחד מאבריו, v'yakhol l'hatzilo b'echad me'evarav,
and we could save the victim with one of the limbs of
the pursuer, ולא הציל, v'lo hitzil, and we did not do that
and we and we killed him, נהרג
עליו, neherag alav, the person who kills the guy to intervene, if
he could've actually just stopped him without killing him, that would actually
be an act of murder. Murder and he would be executed. Now,
of course to execute him you'd have to give התראה, hatra'ah, "Don't
kill him while you're trying to save the guy, only try to
stop him with shooting him in the legs, no, I don't care,
I'm going to kill him anyway, I know what I'm about to
do." Anyway, fine. But whether or not we would actually execute him
in court, the point is, is that it's saying if you could
actually have stopped him without lethal force, then this would be considered
an act of murder. נהרג עליו. neherag alav. מאי טעמא דרבי יונתן
בן שאול? mai ta'ama de'Rabbi Yonatan ben Shaul? So what's the reasoning?
It's interesting that the Gemara does not take this for granted, that
if you could have done it without lethal
force that it was illegitimate, because for the obvious reason that often
if you're trying
overly to be careful and protective of the pursuer, you're not going
to stop him and he's actually going to get through with what
he's doing, right? So there's all these catch—so how much do you
impose this type of a requirement is a very reasonable question. How
much is that protecting the life of the pursuer and how much
is that being irresponsible with saving the life of the victim? So
this is only—this is the position of Rabbi Yonatan ben Shaul. It
is not seen as—we rule this way, but it is not seen
as the universally assumed הלכה. halacha. Okay, so what is the reasoning
of Rabbi Yonatan ben Shaul? דכתיב, dichtiv, you got to love that
name by the way, Yonatan ben Shaul, okay. So what's his reasoning?
דכתיב, dichtiv, the verse says, וכי ינצו אנשים, vechi yinatzu anashim, whatever
when people fight, okay. ואמר רבי אלעזר, v'amar Rabbi Elazar, במצות, bimatzot,
not מצות mitzvos or מצות matzos like whatever, but כי ינצו, ki
yinatzu,
ינצו yinatzu means to fight. So במצות שביניה הכתוב מדבר, bimatzot shebe'neitziah
hakatuv medaber,
it's a fight to the death, okay. How do you know that
they're fighting and they're trying to kill one another? Here's how you
know they're trying to kill one another, דכתיב, dichtiv, ואם יהיה אסון
ונתתה
נפש תחת נפש. ve'im yihye ason venatata nefesh tachat nafesh. If there's
a tragedy, if somebody got killed, then a life for a life.
So if you're going to take the life of the killer, that
means that he was trying to kill the other guy, right? If
he accidentally killed the other guy, it would not—you wouldn't execute him.
So one of the things that the verse says is, these people
are fighting,
and if there's a tragedy, mean if one of them dies, then
you execute the one who killed him. So that must tell us
that they are fighting to the death, they're trying to kill one
another. Because only if they're trying to kill the other person would
you execute them if they succeeded. So that's number one, they're trying
to kill the other person. אי אמרת בשלמא, ee amarta bishlama, now,
ואפילו הכי אמר רחמנא, va'afilu hachi amar Rachmana, nevertheless
the Torah says, ולא יהיה אסון, ve'lo yihye ason, but if there
is no tragedy, and
one of the people hit a woman who's pregnant and causes a
miscarriage. And it says, ענוש יענש, anosh ye'anesh, you have to pay
a fine, okay. So, אי אמרת בשלמא יכול להציל באחד מאיבריו ולא
ניתן להציל בנפשו, ee amarta bishlama yachol lehatzil be'echad me'eivrav velo nitan
lehatzil b'nafsho,
so if you say that if you could intervene and stop the
guy without using lethal force, you're not allowed to use lethal force,
then I would tell you, היינו דמשכחת לה דעניש. hainu d'meshkachat lah
de'anish.
That's why if the woman is hit and miscarries, you'd have to
pay a fine. Why? כגון שיכול להציל באחד מאיבריו. kegon sheyachol lehatzil
be'echad me'eivrav. It's a case where you could have intervened without lethal
force.
I'm going to draw a picture. I don't know why I need
a picture, I feel I need a picture here. Okay.
So, here's the two guys, okay, that's a fist, my two
fists, looks like they're in a boxing match, okay, fine. They're having
a fight, okay. Now, it says that if one of them dies,
it says נפש תחת נפש, nefesh tachat nafesh, right? נפש תחת נפש,
nefesh tachat nafesh,
which means that they're trying to kill each other. Because if one
of them dies, if you execute the other one, then it must
only be—when do you execute somebody? Only if they try to kill
each other. So that's what it says, מצות, matzut, which means a
fight, כי ינצו ki yinatzu שביניה הכתוב מדבר, shebe'neitziah hakatuv medaber, they're
trying to kill one another. Good, they're trying to kill each other.
That's ואם יהיה אסון ונתתה נפש תחת נפש. ve'im yihye ason venatata
nefesh tachat nafesh. Now let's say there's no אסון, ason, this guy
doesn't die, but here's this innocent woman bystander here, right, pregnant woman
bystander, and he hits her
accidentally, and she miscarries, right? So then it says ענוש יענש. anosh
ye'anesh. All right,
so he was trying to kill him and he caused a miscarriage,
he has to pay money. All right, he pays a fine. So
the question is going to be, why would he pay a fine?
If he's trying to kill him, he's a pursuer, you're allowed to
kill this guy to stop him from killing the other person. So
he is—he could be killed. Once he's—if he's doing an act that
he could be killed for, he's not liable the monetary payment, right?
That's that idea of קים ליה kim leh that we've been dealing
with. So how is it that he would ever have to pay
in this case if he's doing an act that he could be
killed for? So therefore, says Rabbi Yonatan ben Shaul, that shows you
there's a case like this we couldn't kill him. What would be
a case like this that he's trying to kill this guy that
we couldn't kill him? If we could neutralize him באחד מאיבריו. be'echad
me'eivrav. So because... If a case where we could neutralize him באחד
מאיבריו, be’echad me’eivarav, we're not allowed to kill him. And therefore, since
we're not allowed to kill him, when he causes a miscarriage, he
has to pay, because he wouldn't be
liable, monetary compensation, because he's not in the process of doing an
act for which we can kill him. Because we can't kill him
right now, we can only neutralize him באחד מאיבריו. be’echad me’eivarav. So
that is the proof of this principle of באחד מאיבריו. be’echad me’eivarav.
So let's take a look.
Okay, so בשלמא, Bishlama, go pick up from three lines before the
lines grow wide. בשלמא יכול להצילו באחד מאיבריו לא ניתן להצילו בנפשו,
Bishlama yachol lehatzilo be’echad me’eivarav lo nitan lehatzilo benafsho, if, if you
could neutralize him with one of his limbs, you can't take his
life. היינו דמשכחת דעניש, Hainu demashkachat de’aneish,
that's why he could be paying if he caused a
miscarriage, כגון שיכול להצילו באחד מאיבריו, kegon sheyachol lehatzilo be’echad me’eivarav, and
therefore he couldn't be killed even though he was trying to kill
the other guy. אלא אי אמרת יכול להצילו באחד מאיבריו נמי ניתן
להצילו בנפשו, Ela ee amrat yachol lehatzilo be’echad me’eivarav nami nitan lehatzilo
benafsho, but if in such a case we also had a license
to use lethal force, היינו דמשכחת דעניש, Hainu demashkachat de’aneish,
so why would he ever have to pay in this case? We
could have killed him and therefore he shouldn't be liable having to
pay. So the גמרא Gemara says no. דילמא שאני הכא דמיתה לזה
ותשלומים לזה. Dilma shani hacha demisa lizeh vetashlumin lizeh. Maybe the reason
here he pays is because it is death to one person and
payment to another person. Meaning, the principle of קים ליה, Kimlei, maybe
it is limited to cases when the person with whom you are
sort of doing the act that you're liable the death penalty is
the person to whom you would be liable compensation. So if somebody,
let's say, shoots someone and ruins their shirt because the bullet goes
through their shirt, right, the person to whom they are liable the
death penalty because of, they're trying to murder ראובן, Reuven, is the
person they would have to compensate. So therefore, therefore
it neutralizes any payment because in that act of killing ראובן Reuven
you can't be liable money to ראובן. Reuven. But let's say, in
the act of trying to kill ראובן, Reuven, the bullet went through
your stained glass window, and then it proceeded on to kill ראובן.
Reuven. Okay, so in that case, actually, they're completely two separate cases:
an act of murder of ראובן Reuven and an act of damages
to you. It's like one is ראובן Reuven takes the guy to
court, whatever ראובן's Reuven relatives for the murder, okay, and you take
the guy to court, and they're unrelated cases. Yes, it was the
same physical act, but maybe we wouldn't say קים ליה Kimlei there
because it's not, since there are different litigants as it were, or
victims, they're seen as completely separate court cases, okay? So that's the
case of
ממון לזה ותשלומים לזה. mammon lizeh vetashlumin lizeh. So we could kill
this guy to protect this victim, so any damage he does to
him he wouldn't have to pay for. Okay, but for this woman,
a different victim, okay, it's a completely different case. So even though
he could be killed, that was about his relationship with him, this
is about what's his relationship to her, it's completely different and therefore
we would not say קים ליה. Kimlei. Now, it might have to
be a case where he's not her husband. Since the תורה Torah
says that the money that is paid is paid to the husband,
okay, even though she's the one to whom it's being done, if
he's the husband, it might be the same case. But if he's
not the husband, then it's a separate case. Yes.
If
still, though, the person can be stopped by holding him back by
his limbs instead of killing him, and he injured the person in
the fight, does he have to pay him damages or not?
Yeah, yeah, you would never say a קים ליה Kimlei idea if
you're not dealing with something that's punishable by death. Yes, so the
answer is yes. If it's יכול להצילו באחד מאיבריו, yachol lehatzilo be’echad
me’eivarav, then he would have to pay anybody damages. It could completely
leave that category of a death, an act deserving of death that
overrides other payments, other things.
Is he deserving of death even though he was stopped by holding
his limb? Because he intends to kill him?
Yes, that's what I'm saying. So once it's no longer deserving of
death, then yes, he would have to pay. The only time he
wouldn't have to pay is if he's doing something. So if it
could be stopped with one of his limbs, then whoever he is
damaging and whatever obligation, whatever compensation he incurs, he would have to
pay.
And he doesn't get killed, right? Because he was stopped. Right, right,
exactly.
Okay, okay. דילמא שאני הכא דמיתה לזה ותשלומים לזה. Dilma shani hacha
demisa lizeh vetashlumin lizeh. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, you know what, לא שנא. lo shna.
I don't buy that, says the גמרא, Gemara, that just
because you can divide it, this person payment, this person death, that
it doesn't override. I would say even in that case it would
override. Why do you say that? דאמר רבא, D’amar Rava, רבא Rava
says, רודף שהיה רודף אחר חבירו ושיבר את הכלים בין של נרדף
בין של כל אדם פטור. Rodeif shehaya rodeif achar chaveiro veshibar es
hakeilim bein shel nirdaf bein shel kol adam patur. So you have
a pursuer running after somebody and in the act of trying to
kill this guy, he broke things. Whether he broke things of the
victim or he broke things of some third party, פטור, patur, he's
exempt. מאי טעמא, Mai ta’ama, what's the reason? מתחייב בנפשו הוא. Mischayav
benefesh hu. He's doing an act that he could be killed for,
and therefore any payment that he is incurring, he's not obligated it.
And that's a perfect case of מיתה לזה ותשלומים לזה, misa lizeh
vetashlumin lizeh, right? It's exactly like the case about shooting through the
window and breaking somebody else's glass window. Okay, running after ראובן Reuven
but breaking שמעון's Shimon vessels. And the point is he doesn't have
to pay שמעון. Shimon. So we don't say that it makes a
difference if they're different people. If the guy is doing an act
that he's liable to death penalty, he doesn't pay any payment. Doesn't
matter to whom those payments would be going. Okay, so therefore, just
to end it, since if he were doing an act that he
could be killed for, he would not have to make any payment.
And nevertheless he has to make payments, that's the proof that we
say that יכול להצילו באחד מאיבריו yachol le-hatzilo b'echad mei-evarav you're not
allowed to kill him. All right? But now, everybody get that, right?
Yes, right? So since in this case he would have to pay
her, excuse me, since even though she's a different person, if he
were doing an act that he could be killed for, there would
be no payment, and nevertheless the תורה Torah tells us there's payment,
that teaches us there are times he's doing this act he can't
be killed, which is that you could stop him with one of
his limbs. All right, but now we're going to continue with רבא's
Rava statement. So the first part of רבא's Rava statement is that
the רודף rodef is exempt even if he breaks the vessels of
a third person. מתחייב בנפשו הוא. mit-chayeiv b'nafsho hu. Fine. Now, let's
continue with this. והניזק ששיבר את הכלים, v'ha-nizak she-shibar et ha-keilim, how
about the victim, the pursued? He broke vessels. של רודף, shel rodef,
so if he had to break vessels of the pursuer in trying
to escape from him, פטור, patur, he's exempt. של כל אדם, shel
kol adam, but if he had to break vessels of a third
party, חייב, chayav, he's חייב. chayav. What's the reason? שרודף פטור שלא
יהא ממונו חביב עליו מגופו. she-rodef patur she-lo yehei mamono chaviv alav
mi-gufo. Well, for the רודף rodef he's exempt because since you could
kill the רודף rodef to save the victim, so if you have
to break the רודף's rodef vessels in order for him to make
an escape of course, he has a license to do that and
somebody else has a license to do that, right? Once the guy
has forfeited his life and anything to be done against his person
to save the victim, if something could be done against his person
to save him, it could be done against his property to save
him. Okay, that's why you're exempt for the property of the רודף.
rodef. Okay, but של כל אדם חייב. shel kol adam chayav. Now
why is however he liable if he breaks a third party's vessels?
שמציל עצמו בממון חבירו, she-matzil atzmo b'mamon chaveiro, because you are saving
your life with your friend's property. And even though of course you're
allowed to do that, although there is a רש"י Rashi in בבא
קמא Bava Kamma that sounds like you might not be allowed to
do that, but we're going to bracket that. The general assumption is
of course you're allowed to do that, it's פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh.
All right? So even though you're allowed to do that, you still
okay, why should this third party, like why should he have to,
or what's the line from Fiddler on the Roof? Just 'cause you
had a bad day, why should I suffer? Right? So just 'cause
you're trying to save your life, why does that mean I have
to pay for it? So you have to compensate me, okay? Sure
you were entitled to do that, you do what you have to
do to save your life, but you broke my stuff, pay me
for it. Okay. Now, ורודף שהיה רודף אחר רודף להצילו. v'rodef she-hayah
rodef achar rodef le-hatzilo. Now here's the third case. A pursuer is
pursuing the pursuer, meaning the let's call him, excuse me for this
term, the Good Samaritan, is going ahead and trying to intervene and
stop the pursuer from killing the victim. ושיבר את הכלים, v'shibar et
ha-keilim, and in the attempt of trying to stop the pursuer this
Good Samaritan is breaking vessels. ושיבר את הכלים, בין של רודף בין
של נירדף, בין של כל אדם, v'shibar et ha-keilim, bein shel rodef
bein shel nirdaf, bein shel kol adam, whether the vessels of the
pursuer or of the victim or of a third party, פטור, patur,
he's פטור. patur. Now let's figure that out. Why is he exempt
from the vessels of the pursuer? That makes sense, right? If you
could take the life of the pursuer, you could destroy his property
to save the guy. Why is he exempt from the vessels of
the victim? Well, you could assume that the victim would want him
to do this, and it would not be considered an act of
damage to the victim to use the victim's money to save the
victim's life. But why is he exempt when he breaks the vessels
of a third party? Right? If the victim has to pay, why
is this guy exempt when he breaks the vessels of a third
party?
Is he getting any advantage from?
True, but we don't say saving your life is like an advantage,
it's like everybody is obligated to save your life, a third party
is obligated to save your life. It's true. Where? In הניזק. ha-nizak.
Right,
the third party whose vessels, the fourth party whose vessels were broken
would also be obligated if they were standing by to try to
save him and so therefore his vessels become obligated in some way.
Okay, that's interesting, but if that's true then when the pursued broke
those vessels they should also be exempt. Right? Now it also by
the way gets to an interesting question what Judah said, which is
what the question we raised before. When you have to go ahead
and save somebody's life and exert yourself, what are we demanding of
you? The גמרא Gemara said we're demanding of you remember the גמרא
Gemara said to even hire people. But the גמרא Gemara didn't say
is can I get compensated if I hire people. Okay, I had
to go take put my hand in my pocket, hire people, whatever
to save this guy. After now this guy is saved, can I
go to him and give him the bill? Right? I think that
happens sometimes, like if somebody's drowning and the government has to send
a helicopter and save the guy or whatever, like there are times
where they could actually present the guy the bill afterwards, you
know? So one would... it's certainly it would sound one way to
understand it is, yes, you would have to pay because if, because
if you would say that, well, and because wait a minute, right,
because if, going back to the other case, if when they broke
David's vessels in trying to save their own lives, if David would
have to spend money to intervene to save the life, so then
why do they have to compensate you for breaking your vessel? You
had an obligation to help out, you would have had to spend
money. So it's quite likely that even though he might have to
spend money, he's allowed to be compensated. So when the person breaks
your vessel, they have to compensate you. So now we're back to
the question, which is why when you're trying to be the good
Samaritan and you break a vessel, do you not have to pay
compensation? So wait, wait, let's see. Loria has an answer.
Social policy that you don't
want to discourage people from intervening. Exactly. That's why I used the
term good Samaritan. So let's read the next line of the גמרא.
Gemara. Wait, wait, let me read the next line of the גמרא.
Gemara. ולא מן הדין. Vlo min hadin. This is really not legally
true. As a point of real law, this guy who's intervening should
have to pay if he broke a third party's vessels. שאם אי
אתה אומר כן, She'im i atah omer ken, but if you don't
say this, נמצא אין אדם שמציל את חבירו מיד הרודף. Nimtza ein
adam shematzil et chaveiro miyad harodeif.
Nobody's going to want to intervene because nobody's going to say, "what,
I'm going to intervene and I'm going to try to do a
good thing and then they're going to present me with a bill?"
So you know, forget this. Okay, and this by the way is
what the good Samaritan law is. By the way, the good Samaritan
was also, I should just mention, a whole critique of the פרושים,
Perushim, of the you know, in the time of Jesus, of the
rabbis, because the whole point
was, "oh you know, whatever, you only care about your own." It's
this good Samaritan, this outsider, this שומרוני, Shomroni, this you know, who's
on the outside of society, he cares about the person on the
street, you know, who's also like marginalized and so on. So just
so you should be aware of the context of that phrase. But
the good Samaritan law, against what people believe, does not obligate somebody
to intervene. Okay, הלכה Halacha obligates somebody to intervene. The secular law
does not obligate you. You want, somebody's there drowning in the ocean,
says "help, help, throw me the life preservers," and you say "no"
and you walk away, you cannot be held liable. You have no
obligation to intervene. I, but the good Samaritan law is if you
jump in after him and you try to save him and in
dragging him out of the river you break his leg, he can't
present you with a doctor bill afterwards. If to protect you if
you are, you know, in good faith trying to help the guy.
And that's a policy issue, and that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara
says here. Yeah, Jenna.
Can we go back to the middle case where the נרדף nirdaph
breaks the third person, third party's vessel? Right.
And he has to pay.
Why is he having to pay and not the רודף?
rodeif?
Well, because he's the
מזיק. mazik.
He's only a מזיק? mazik?
Yeah, because somebody forced him into that situation, I guess, but it's
sort of like a good point. I guess it's sort of like
the אדם מועד לעולם, adam mu'ad l'olam, you know? Like if even
if you're totally not at fault, if you're the one to have
broken something, you're the one who has to pay it. Like we
don't deal with an issue of negligence and causation by by damage,
by when you personally are מזיק mazik something. I know it does
sound weird. It's a good point. You're saying, meaning why not just
say the רודף rodeif is like if I were to, for example,
because an exception to the rule of אדם מועד לעולם adam mu'ad
l'olam is if I were to pick David up and, if I
had if I was that big, and I was strong and I
was to throw him down on some vase and break the vase,
David wouldn't have to pay because I'm using David. I'm the מזיק
mazik and I'm using David. Right? So, but when somebody's running after,
why don't you see it the same way? It's like he threw
the guy on the vessel. Yeah, it's a good question. It's a
good question. I don't know. I wonder also, yeah, it's a good
question. I mean we don't, but I appreciate the question.
Yeah. You said the third party also had the responsibility in to
take part and that's why his vessels should be his obligation, but
what if he's not even there?
Right, so that right, I understand. Yeah, yeah, so that's the question.
You could distinguish those cases. Anyway, that's not clear, which is when
the person is involved and actively saving and spending his own money,
then you could say you're actively doing the מצווה, mitzvah, maybe you're
not compensated, maybe you are. That's not less clear. Okay, but when
your vessels are being used without you, then you can get compensated
in that case. Okay. So let's now
continue. אבל הרודף אחר בהמה, Aval harodeif achar behemah, person pursuing the
animal, since there's no real victim there, you cannot intervene with lethal
force. תניא. Tanya. Now we're going to say what we quoted yesterday.
רבי שמעון בן יוחנן אומר Rebbe Shimon ben Yochanan omer העובד עבודה
זרה ניתן להציל בנפשו. ha'oveid avodah zarah nitan lehatzil b'nafsho. Somebody's going
to do עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, you can stop them with lethal
force. So it seems like this is not about a victim idea,
it's about an עבירה aveirah idea. מקל וחומר. Mikal vachomer. But let's
see how he learns it out, a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה
פגם הדיוט ניתן להציל בנפשו, U'mah pegam hedyot nitan lehatzil b'nafsho, when
it's a you know when it's a lay person, a human to
save them from being disgraced you can you know you can use
lethal force to save them from becoming the victim. פגם גבוה לא
כל שכן? Pegam gavoah lo kol shekein? So when it's God, to
save God from this injury okay how much more so can you
use lethal force. So it's a fascinating idea. Remember when we spoke
the other day about עבודה זרה avodah zarah I said well it
sounds like here it's just about the עבירה, aveirah, not about the
victim. And I said no maybe there is a victim, maybe the
society is
a victim, right? So this is making the victim not the society,
it's making the victim God. God's honor is being violated. This woman's
honor is being violated, God's honor is being violated. So an act
of עבודה זרה avodah zarah is a violation of God's honor. Now
I wonder if it's just the act of עבודה זרה avodah zarah
that's a violation of God's honor, or if it's the act of
עבודה זרה avodah zarah that nobody is doing anything to intervene about
is a violation of God's honor. You know what I'm saying? Like
it's the fact that the community is allowing it and tolerating it
is part of what causes the חילול השם. chillul Hashem. Or is
it just saying that maybe the simpler sense is just no, little
guy is doing עבודה זרה avodah zarah in his own little private
room and nobody knows about it, but like to me that's harder.
Like we're not saying it's בפרהסיא. be-farhesya. Even if it's in
private. So anyway, so he could just be saying objectively that's violating
God's honor, or it could be that by not intervening it's it
creates a violation of God's honor. And therefore we have to intervene.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, וכי עונשין מן
הדין? vekhi onshin min ha-din? Now can you use punish, or even
though this is not necessarily a court punishment, but you know use
a physical force based on a קל וחומר? kal va-chomer? Yes, קסבר
עונשין מן הדין. kasavar onshin min ha-din. Yes, with שמואל, Shmuel, yes,
you can use a קל וחומר kal va-chomer to teach you to
use lethal force.
תניא, Tanya, we learn a ברייתא, beraita, רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi
Elazar berabbi Shimon אומר, omer, המחלל את השבת ניתן להצילו בנפשו. ham-chalel
et ha-Shabbat nitan le-hatzilo be-nafsho. If someone violates שבת, Shabbat, he can
be saved with his life. So you can use lethal force. So
סבר לה כאבוה, savar lah ke-avuh, so first he holds like his
father רבי שמעון בר יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, דאמר עונשין מן
הדין, de-amar onshin min ha-din, that you can sort of use this
קל וחומר kal va-chomer to use lethal force in the case of
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. ואתיא שבת מחילול חילול מעבודת כוכבים, va-atya Shabbat
me-chillul chillul me-avodat kochavim, and we link שבת Shabbat to עבודה זרה
avodah zarah because of the use of the word חילול chillul in
the verse. Okay, and therefore and often we say שבת Shabbat is
like עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So a violation of שבת Shabbat is
a similar violation of God's honor and therefore we have to use
lethal force in order to defend God's honor. So again I would
sort of also make it like I said a little bit more
of a violation of the community, but even if it's a violation
of God's honor, maybe violation because if we're allowing חילול שבת chillul
Shabbat to occur among us and we are not doing anything about
it, that becomes like a violation of God's honor. So we don't
rule that way but that's what's behind their position.
Right, they were just like the zealots when they went and they
killed right and they were very zealous.
Exactly, or you ever try people try to drive through מאה שערים
Meah Shearim and get the stones thrown at them right? So obviously
that's not consistent with our more pluralistic attitudes, but you sort of,
but I think from their perspective if somebody is driving in their
neighborhood and they're not reacting, then that's like then they're saying they're
okay with it, right? So it almost becomes like a, so that
seems like it's the logic here behind it. Okay, אמר רבי יוחנן
משום רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק. Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben
Yehotzadak.
Now we shift gears and this is like a lot of people
like you'd see why this גמרא, Gemara, why this פרק perek is
so rich. Like we just have this whole thing of רודף rodef
which is fascinating and now we get to the classic גמרא Gemara
about יהרג ואל יעבור, yehareg ve-al ya'avor, about when do you have
to give up your life. Because if we're talking about intervening and
taking somebody's life to protect a victim, and then it moved a
little bit to taking somebody's life to protect them from doing a
certain type of an עבירה, aveirah, then we have to talk about
when are you supposed to be giving up your own life rather
than doing a certain type of a sin. Okay, so אמר רבי
יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק, Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon
ben Yehotzadak, נמנו וגמרו בעליית בית נתזה בלוד. nimnu ve-gamru ba-aliyat beit
Nitza be-Lod. They they took a vote in the attic of this
guy נתזה Nitza in לוד. Lod. לוד, Lod,
excuse me. I keep saying לוד, Lod, it's לוד, Lod, right? What
is it? לוד? Lod? It's לוד, Lod, לוד, Lod, right? But לוד.
Lod. I'm just thinking of the airport you go to. כל עבירות
שבתורה, kol aveirot she-ba-Torah, all the עבירות, aveirot, אם אומרים לאדם עבור
ואל תהרג, im omrim le-adam avor ve-al ttehareg,
transgress and don't be killed, יעבור ואל יהרג, ya'avor ve-al yehareg,
you should transgress and not be killed. חוץ מעבודה זרה וגילוי עריות
ושפיכות דמים, chutz me-avodah zarah ve-gilluy arayot u-shefikhut damim,
with the exception of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, גילוי עריות gilluy arayot
and שפיכות דמים. shefikhut damim. Now we're going to speak about where
we learned those three out from, but I want to just say
something that occurred to me as I was preparing the דף daf
which is all of those three
are, two of them and then the third is debated, are exactly
what we've just been talking about. We just said you kill somebody
before rather than letting them commit murder. We said you kill somebody
rather than letting them do an act of גילוי עריות gilluy arayot
in certain cases. And we now had the opinion of רבי שמעון
בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai that says you kill somebody before
or whatever it was, רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar berabbi Shimon
that you no, רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai that
you kill somebody before letting them do עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So
all those three cases are cases where you might have to intervene
use lethal force to stop the person for doing it and now
we're saying therefore the person himself has to give up their own
life rather than doing it. Now the gap is is that we
don't פסקן pasken when it comes to עבודה זרה avodah zarah you
don't use lethal force to stop a person from doing עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, but a person does have to give up his own
life. So they don't exactly overlap but it's very interesting the parallels.
Okay, so...
So the gemara says like this. והתניא vehatanya but don't we teach
in a ברייתא? braita? I'm sorry, okay. ועובד כוכבים? veoved kochavim? Now
it doesn't give any basis for it. Okay. ועובד כוכבים לא? veoved
kochavim lo? Are you is it really? Is that really true that
you're not supposed to do עבודה זרה avoda zara and you're supposed
to give up your life? והתניא vehatanya we taught in a ברייתא,
braita, אמר רבי ישמעאל, amar Rabbi Yishmael, מנין שאם אמרו לו לאדם
עבוד עבודת כוכבים ואל תהרג, minayin sheim amru lo leadam avod avodat
kochavim veal tehareg,
if they say to a guy worship עבודה זרה avoda zara and
don't get killed, מנין שיעבוד ואל יהרג? minayin sheyaavod veal yehareg? How
do you know that you're supposed to worship? Which is shocking to
us because we're always brought up right עבודה זרה avoda zara is
one of the three. But I also want to remind us that
he's not talking about like you have to convert, right? He's saying
is no, I just want to see you put this sacrifice on
this altar to Zeus, right? It's a particular, specific, concrete act, okay?
It's not giving up your Jewish identity and converting. So he says
yeah, go ahead, big deal, do the act. Okay, you're being forced.
Okay, you're still so how and you're allowed to. How do you
know you're allowed to? תלמוד לומר וחי בהם ולא שימות בהם. talmud
lomar vechai bahem velo sheyamut bahem. The same verse we use to
say why you're allowed to do any other עבירה aveira he says
עבודה זרה avoda zara is no different. You know what? God can
handle it. God understands that you're being forced, okay? So look, עבודה
זרה avoda zara is not one of the big three. Okay. יכול
אפילו בפרהסיא yachol afilu befarhesya
now maybe if in public you also should do it? No, תלמוד
לומר ולא תחללו את שם קדשי ונקדשתי talmud lomar velo techalelu et
shem kodshi venikdashti
and the end of the פסוק pasuk is בתוך בני ישראל. betoch
bnei yisrael. I'll be sanctified among the people of Israel. When it's
in public you have to and there's an obvious difference, right? An
act of public martyrdom is basically saying like you know you have
to sort of you know if in public everybody sees you worship
עבודה זרה avoda zara rather than put to death then there's saying
is like okay it's more important for us to you know go
against like give up our religion, right? עבודה זרה avoda zara represents
more even though I just said it was a specific concrete act,
it might be a concrete act but it's more symbolic of giving
up your religion you know defying your God than violating a particular
commandment. So when it's done in public the sort of impact that
that has in terms of leading others to abandon God you know
saying that your life is more important than your faith and so
on, right? And then the קידוש השם kiddush Hashem that happens when
it's an act of public martyrdom that sends the opposite message that
my faith is more important than my life, right? That occurs in
public. But he says but what's the point of that in private?
In private it doesn't have that symbolic meaning and it doesn't have
that larger implication. It's just you and the guy and God. So
in private you do עבודה זרה avoda zara but in public it's
an act of martyrdom. Okay. ונקדשתי, venikdashti,
okay actually you know I mean if we could get out of
our normal mindset where we always put עבודה זרה avoda zara there,
there's a certain logic to compelling logic to this right? It's a
different type of an act in public and in private, you know,
assume that עבודה זרה avoda zara means like I said a concrete
act and not a whole abandonment of the faith. So anyway so
why do we put עבודה זרה avoda zara in the list? It
says איהו דאמר כרבי אליעזר ihu deamar keRabbi Eliezer because he is
holding like Rabbi Eliezer, דתניא detanya we taught in a ברייתא braita
רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer ואהבת את ה' אלהיך בכל לבבך
veahavta et Hashem Elokecha bechol levavecha
love Hashem
your God with all your life ובכל נפשך ובכל מאדך uvechol nafshecha
uvechol meodecha and all your soul and all your heart. אם נאמר
בכל נפשך למה נאמר בכל מאדך? im neemar bechol nafshecha lama neemar
bechol meodecha?
So it says with all your soul why does it say with
all your wealth, all your possessions? ואם נאמר בכל מאדך למה נאמר
בכל נפשך? veim neemar bechol meodecha lama neemar bechol nafshecha? And
if it says your possessions why did it say your life? Because
אם יש לך אדם שגופו חביב עליו מממונו, im yesh lecha adam
shegufo chaviv alav mimamono, if you have somebody that their body that
their life is more important to them than their property, לכך נאמר
בכל נפשך, lekach neemar bechol nafshecha,
it says with all your life you have to give up your
life in order to show your love of God. ואם יש לך
אדם שממונו חביב עליו מגופו, veim yesh lecha adam shemamono chaviv alav
migufo, and if you have
somebody whose money is more valuable than their life I never knew
who that person is that would rather keep their money and die
but I don't know anyway so לכך נאמר בכל מאדך lekach neemar
bechol meodecha all your all your... I know that's I was going
to say that the Jack Benny line. The guy says your money
or your life and he says I'm thinking, I'm thinking. Right. So
anyway, okay. Anyway, so where do we learn it from? So we
learn it not from and this is the important paradigm shift. It's
true as you're saying in private an act of עבודה זרה avoda
zara is not an act of חילול השם chilul Hashem and קידוש
השם. kiddush Hashem. That's only in public. But in private it still
is an act of אהבת השם, ahavat Hashem, okay? And when somebody
is saying worship another God even if it's not giving up your
faith even if it's only a specific concrete act, you are basically
more than any עבירה aveira you are basically you know completely sort
of abandoning God in that moment even if you and giving your
love if you sort of think about that you know your fidelity
at that moment even for that one act, right? I mean an
act of adultery also might not be an ongoing relationship but it's
a one act which undermines the fidelity of the relationship, right? So
that is a contradiction of אהבת השם. ahavat Hashem. And therefore since
אהבת השם ahavat Hashem has to be בכל נפשך bechol nafshecha you
have to be prepared to give up your life rather than to
compromise that expression of you know I would sort of say fidelity
to God. Okay. So that's a different idea then it's even in
private, okay? And it's even just between you. It's not between what
it says to other people. You have to know for yourself that
you cannot violate your... fidelity to God even for one moment, okay,
and that it's worth giving up your life for that. Okay, so
that's where he learns it out from, and that's why we make
the ruling that עבודה זרה avodah zarah you give up your life
even in private. But again I want to make the point that
notice the one of those three that's questioned whether you give up
your life for them is עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. The same way
when it came to intervening to protecting the victim, it's all agreed
that we intervene to save the murder victim or the rape victim,
and it's debated if we intervene in the case of עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. And the same way here by martyrdom, whether you give
up your life for עבודה זרה avodah zarah is an area of
debate. Again, the פסק psak is different, we פוסק pasken you give
up your life for עבודה זרה avodah zarah as an act of
martyrdom even in private, but you don't intervene with lethal force to
stop somebody from doing an act of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So
there is a division of those, yes.
I could see in public because of the effect on the community.
Right. In private, Hashem knows that you're not really doing this with
intention. Right.
Right, I mean that is true. You could say that it's not
even a violation of אהבת השם Ahavat Hashem because you're not doing
it willingly, you're doing it when it's forced. But it seems like
that's the point of the בכל נפשך bechol nafshecha that you know
you have to show that you love God so much, right, that
you would not do an act of, you know, of giving your
fealty to another God even under compulsion, even under threat of life,
right? So that's the point, right? Meaning, yes, God ultimately knows what's
in your heart, but nevertheless what you have to demonstrate that your
love is so great. Like you know what about a case a
man is, you know, whatever, or a woman has to commit adultery
under force, right? So again, I'm not saying that she should do
it, but this
is between Hashem and you basically. It's not a physical act, right?
And if you're saying to yourself I'm not doing this, this is
just for show.
Right, well that gets also to our previous whole discussion about about
like if it's not מאהבה me'ahava or מיראה, mi'yirah, it's not even
really an act of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Yeah, I understand, I
mean I think that that informs the position that says you don't
give up your life. Yeah, Jenna?
Does everyone hold that it's only, that it applies in, and I
thought I remember the רמב"ם Rambam holding like...
There's going to be another public element about other עבירות. aveirot. Okay,
these three are even in private and that's why we had to
prove, the debate was, wait, wait, is that really true about עבודה
זרה avodah zarah in private? And because obviously the case of murder
and rape or whatever עריות arayot are an act against another person.
So the public/private doesn't matter,
it's about doing an act against another person. But by עבודה זרה
avodah zarah we have to say, wait, wait, is עבודה זרה avodah
zarah really limited to private? Maybe, yeah, yeah, עבודה זרה avodah zarah
also only in private. Others will have a public aspect, right, but
one of the three maybe
if they're public, exactly.
These three you give up your life even in
private, and that's why we were debating whether that was true by
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Okay, but now we're going to continue with
the others, but first we have to explain the case of murder
and גילוי עריות. giluy arayot. Okay, so let's take a look. גילוי
עריות ושפיכות דמים, giluy arayot u'shfichut damim, so where do you know
that you give up your life rather than doing an act of
גילוי עריות giluy arayot and
murder? כי דרבי, Ki de'Rabbi, like Rabbi, דתניא, detanya, it's in a
ברייתא, braita, רבי אומר, Rabbi Omer, כי כאשר יקום איש על רעהו
ורצחו נפש כן הדבר הזה. Ki ka'asher yakum ish al re'ehu u'retzacho
nefesh ken hadavar hazeh. As a man would rise up against somebody
and murder him, so is this thing, this thing about this woman
who's been raped. וכי מה למדנו מרצח מעתה? Ve'chi ma lamadnu merotze'ach
me'ata?
What do we need to learn from the example of murder? So
we are to discuss already saying that the girl is blameless, that
obviously was a חידוש chiddush in ancient society and so on. But
the גמרא Gemara wants to say legally what's the point of connecting
it to murder? Okay, הרי זה בא ללמד ונמצא למד. Harei zeh
ba lelamed ve'nimtza lamed. So the first thing is what we said
yesterday, the idea of murder is coming to teach something and it
winds up learning. What's it learning? מקיש רוצח לנערה המאורסה. Makish rotze'ach
l'na'arah ham'orasah. מה נערה המאורסה ניתן להצילה בנפשו? Ma na'arah ham'orasah nitan
le'hatzilah benafsho? The same way by this betrothed maiden you can use
lethal force to protect her because אין מושיע לה ein moshia lah
like we said yesterday. אף רוצח ניתן להצילה בנפשו. Af rotze'ach nitan
le'hatzilo benafsho. So the link tells you that you can use lethal
force to intervene and to stop a guy from committing murder. Okay,
ומקיש, U'makish, but now we're going to say the part two, ומקיש
נערה המאורסה
לרוצח. u'makish na'arah ham'orasah l'rotze'ach. מה רוצח יהרג ואל יעבור? Ma rotze'ach
ye'hareg ve'al ya'avor? The same way by murder it's obvious that you
should die rather than allowing your, rather than, you should allow yourself
to die rather than committing murder. So the same way that we
take that for granted by murder, so אף, Af, where are we,
אף נערה המאורסה תהרג ואל תעבור. af na'arah ham'orasah te'hareg ve'al ta'avor.
Even by נערה המאורסה na'arah ham'orasah she should be killed rather than
transgressing. Okay, so it's the same idea that the same way by
רציחה retzichah you give up your life, by גילוי עריות giluy arayot
you also give up your life. So the גמרא Gemara says, ורוצח
גופו מנלן? Verotze'ach gufo minalan? So where do you know by murder
that you give up
your life rather than committing murder? So the גמרא Gemara says, סברא
הוא. sevara hu. That we just know from סברא. sevara. דההוא דאתא
לקמיה דרבה, De'hahu de'ata l'kamei de'Rabbah, somebody came to Rabbah ואמר ליה,
v'amar lei, and said to him, אמר לי מרי דוראי, amar li
mari durai, the master of my city, the non-Jewish governor of my
city said to me, זיל קטליה לפלניא, zil katleih l'panya, go kill
so-and-so, ואי לא קטלינא לך, v'ei lo katlina lach, and if you
don't I'm going to kill you. So what should I do? So
אמר ליה, amar lei, so רבא Rava said to him, ליקטלוך ולא
תיקטול, liktlocha velo tiktol, let him kill you and don't you be
the one to commit murder. Why? מי יימר דדמא דידך סומק
טפי? Mi yeimar de-dama didach sumak tfei? Who says your blood is
any redder than his? דילמא דמא דההוא גברא סומק טפי. Dilma dama
de-hahu gavra sumak tfei. Maybe his blood is redder than yours. Why
should you value your life over his? To protect your life, you're
going to take the other person's life, right? Better, you know, you,
so you know,
don't do anything, let that guy take your life, but you don't
have a right, you know, one way to say it is, your
right to self-protection, and you do have a right to protect yourself
before everybody else, you actually have an obligation to protect yourself before
everybody else, חייך וחיי חברך חייך קודמין, Chayecha ve-chayei chavercha chayecha kodmin,
but that right does not come at the expense of somebody else's
life, okay? And therefore, you do, you know,
what entitles you to commit murder to protect your life at the
expense of that other person? Now רש״י Rashi has an interesting way
of saying it. רש״י Rashi actually says like this. The reason the
תורה Torah allows you to do an עבירה, aveira, to, to
when somebody told you a gun to your head is because it
wants to protect life, okay? But in this case where a life
is going to be taken regardless, why should it give license to
the עבירה? aveira? All right. So that's a little bit, a little
different than like, why, what entitles you to commit an act of
murder? It's more like any עבירה. aveira. Since a life is going
to be taken regardless, what entitles you to do any עבירה? aveira?
You know, but the whole license to do an עבירה aveira comes
in order to stop a life from being taken. All right. But
anyway, there are interesting questions that are raised. Let's say somebody says,
you know, kill that person or I'm going to kill you and
your whole family, right? So it's not like just one, my blood
versus his, you know? And it's, you know, it's ten people versus
one person, right? There's all these really fascinating questions about what types
of tradeoffs, okay? But anyway, but that's the logic. The logic is,
is that what should give you license to commit murder, to take
a life to save your own, right? That life is no more
valuable than yours. What gives, what permits the act of murder? And
once we say that by murder, we say that by the case
of rape. Now what's interesting about the case of rape is, one
minute, the גמרא Gemara said גילוי עריות. giluy arayot. Before we were
talking about גילוי עריות giluy arayot which was forced, right? But what
about if like the woman isn't forced here? Let's say the woman
is willing and they hold a gun to a guy's head and
say, you know, go ahead and have intercourse with that woman or
we'll kill you. So it seems like it's not anymore about force,
an act of violence against the person, right? It seems like it's,
maybe it is, maybe it's limited to cases when it's like being
forced. But maybe it seems like it's just the act of the
forbidden sexual act. Okay. And then the logic is harder because you
could have cases of force which are not גילוי עריות, giluy arayot,
right? Like a case of, halachically, a rape of an unmarried woman
who is not a נדה, niddah, right? A violent act of rape
or whatever. And that you would say, oh, that you should do,
because that's not גילוי עריות giluy arayot as opposed to, right, as
opposed to a case which is a consensual act of with a
woman who's a נדה niddah and that you're not supposed to do
and give up your life because that is גילוי עריות. giluy arayot.
So what is it about גילוי עריות giluy arayot that makes it
יהרג ואל יעבור? yehareg ve-al ya'avor? It doesn't have the same idea
of the victimhood, right? So that's like a very challenging idea that
I don't think has, people have really grappled with sufficiently. Now maybe
you could try to say that's maybe actually no, what גילוי עריות
giluy arayot does mean is it means in context of force and
in context of whatever, but it doesn't seem like that. It seems
like it's just the act of forbidden sex without that whole idea
of consensual versus forced and so on, even when it's not acts
of violence. Okay. So that's the basic הלכות halachot here. I mean
obviously we can't deal with the whole סוגיא sugya of יהרג ואל
יעבור, yehareg ve-al ya'avor, but here we're getting the foundation of it.
So let's continue. It says like this. Okay. כי אתא רב דימי
אמר רבי יוחנן, Ki asa Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Yochanan, when רב
דימי Rav Dimi came he said in the name of רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, לא שנו אלא שלא בשעת גזירת המלכות. Lo shanu ela
she-lo b'shat gzeirat hamalchut. When is it this, here Janet's going to
the point you said, when is it that other עבירות aveirot you
do rather than, you say rather than give up your life? When
it's not at the time when the government is trying to wipe
out the, the faith, right? When it's not a time of, I
wouldn't just say oppression, but there's gotta be a word for this,
like שמד shmad is what you normally say in Hebrew. Persecution. Yeah,
but persecution could just mean we're trying, like I don't know, we
do pogroms against the Jews. It's systematic persecution. Yeah, but it's, but
it's less about persecuting their bodies and it's more about trying to
wipe out their faith, right? So anyway, גזירת המלכות gzeirat hamalchut is
the government is trying to undermine the faith.
Okay. In that time, אבל בשעת גזירת
המלכות אפילו מצוה קלה יהרג ואל יעבור.
Aval
b'shat gzeirat
hamalchut afilu mitzvah kalla yehareg ve-al ya'avor. Even the most trivial מצוה,
mitzvah, because then it's all about like, you know, once one person
starts giving in, right, they're going to succeed. Like here at this
moment, you know, you gotta protect Judaism and not just, not just
the Jews, not just the Jewish life. The only reason, you know,
they're, it's true like it's, they say this, like the only reason,
you know... Religions have survived is because people were able to give
up, were willing to give up their lives for them, because they
were martyring themselves, which basically said, you know, that this is because
once people are saying, well no, I mean if I'm dead I
can't practice my faith, it's more important for me to protect my
life. Well once people start doing that then the religion gets wiped
out because then everybody succumbs, right? So it's only when people are
willing to martyr themselves, you know, if the government doesn't succeed in
martyring everybody, you know, that it shows that the religion is more
important, that people hold fast to it and that the religion survives.
Okay, so that's בשעת גזירת מלכות. bishas gezeiras malchus. Then as Ravin
said in the name of Rabbi Yochanan, when Ravin came he said
in the name of Rabbi Yochanan, it's interesting to see statements are
in the name of Rabbi Yochanan who is coming from in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael who had a deal with the Romans who had
a deal with times when they were trying to wipe out the
faith, which was not true in בבל. Bavel. Okay, so he said
אפילו שלא בשעת גזירת מלכות, afilu shelo bishas gezeiras malchus, even when
it's not they're not actively trying to wipe out the faith, לא
אמרו אלא בצינעא, lo amru ela betzina, it's only in private, אבל
בפרהסיא, aval befarhesya, in public, אפילו מצוה קלה יהרג ואל יעבור, afilu
mitzvah kalla yeihareg v'al ya'avor, even a light מצוה. mitzvah. Now really?
So we're going to get to that. Somebody just says to me
like I need you to bake me a cake on Shabbos and
if not I'll kill you, I have to give up my life?
Like why is it endangering the whole religion? So the Gemara is
going to say, and not to ruin the surprise, but just to
give you, that it's not just that it's in public. It's that
it's in public and they're in public and they're doing it not
because the guy wants a cake on Shabbos. They're doing it to
make a point, to show, just for the point of getting you
to transgress. So if that's true, even if there's not a government-wide,
you know, policy of trying to undermine the faith, it's in this
one concrete act this person is trying to show in public that
they can get you to transgress and that you'd be willing to
do that rather than give up your life. And in that case
you have to give up your life because once you're willing to
do that and you're showing your willingness to transgress and it's just
for the purpose of transgressing, it's not because the guy needs a
freshly baked cake, right? So that's going to obviously undermine the faith.
Okay, so that's the idea. We just got to keep on going.
אמר רבא בר רב יצחק אמר רב, Amar Rava bar Rav Yitzchak
amar Rav, אפילו לשינויי ערקתא דמסאני, afilu leshinuyei arkasa demisani, even if
it would not even be a הלכה, halacha, even it would just
be a practice to change like your shoelace. Okay, so Rashi sort
of says it's not completely arbitrary, maybe Jews wore more צניעותדיק tzniusdik
shoelaces than non-Jews, I don't know what that means. Okay, but it's
some trivial type of a practice that is not even a הלכה,
halacha, it's just a מנהג, minhag, but it's something that's connected to
Jewish identity and if they're asking you to do it, okay, in
public and again in public in the context of with the intent
of sort of undermining Jewish practice even if it's not government-wide or
whatever, then you give up your life. וכמה פרהסיא, Vekama farhesya, now
how much is public? אמר רב יעקב אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rav
Yaakov amar Rabbi Yochanan, אין פרהסיא פחותה מעשרה בני אדם, ein farhesya
pechusa mei'asara bnei adam, ten people. פשיטא, Pshita, obviously, פשיטא דהישראלים בעינן,
pshita d'Yisraelim ba'inan, it's obvious that we need Jews. דכתיב ונקדשתי בתוך
בני ישראל dechtiv v'nikdashti betoch bnei Yisrael and בני ישראל, bnei Yisrael,
so it's קידוש השם, Kiddush Hashem, this is an act now of
קידוש השם Kiddush Hashem that it's a trivial מצוה, mitzvah, it's not
these other things about מאי חזית דדמא דידך. mai chazis dedama didach.
It's once it's about שעת השמד sha'as hashmad and פרהסיא farhesya and
even a light מצוה, mitzvah, it's all about the act of קידוש
השם, Kiddush Hashem, of martyring yourself, of defending God's name and God's
honor and so on. Okay, and that needs ten Jews. Now, I
should say להלכה lehalacha it's pretty accepted that this is men and
women. There's not an idea of a מנין. minyan. This is an
idea of פרהסיא. farhesya. It's actually an interesting question, when do we
want an idea that something is in public פרהסיא farhesya rather than
an idea that it's like this, you know, mini community defined as
a מנין minyan as men? So for example, to throw to a
completely, well not completely different, we're going to mention אסתר Esther in
a minute, there's a significant opinion that when you do קריאת מגילה
בפרהסיא krias megillah befarhesya and you make the special ברכה bracha when
you make, do it בפרהסיא befarhesya that that is not defined by
ten men and it would be ten men and women. Okay, so
there's an idea of פרהסיא farhesya that's different than an idea of
מנין. minyan. Anyway, so that's ten. Okay, בעי רב ירמיה, ba'ei Rav
Yirmiya, Rav Yirmiya said, תשעה ישראלים ונכרי אחד, tish'ah Yisraelim venochri echad,
let's say nine of them are Jews and one's a non-Jew, מהו,
mahu, what's the הלכה? halacha? תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear,
I don't know why we would think nine and one, like because
the one is the perpetrator. No, but there's other places where we
talk about nine and one, right? Right, but like for מנין minyan
for example we would never consider a non-Jew, but yeah anyway that's
his question. תא שמע, Ta shema, come in here, דתני רב ינאי
אחוה דרבי חייא בר אבא, detani Rav Yannai achuha deRabbi Chiya bar
Abba, אתיא תוך תוך, atya toch toch, we make a גזירה שוה,
gezeira shava, כתיב הכא ונקדשתי בתוך בני ישראל ksiv hacha v'nikdashti betoch
bnei Yisrael וכתיב התם הבדלו מתוך העדה הזאת uchsiv hasam hibadlu mitoch
ha'eidah hazos by the מרגלים, meraglim, מה להלן עשרה, mah lehalan asara,
the same way there there were ten וכולהו ישראל vekulhu Yisrael and
they were all Jews, אף כאן עשרה וכולהו ישראל, af kan asara
vekulhu Yisrael, here the same, which is so funny, like we obviously
knew that link anyway, why were we assuming ten to begin with?
We obviously implicitly understood that you were making that connection to מרגלים,
meraglim, that's always where we learn it from. So once we knew
that, so okay, it's gone. To be ישראל. Yisrael. But then again,
the irony is that if you use that same בתוך בני ישראל
betoch B'nei Yisrael to tell you ten for מניין minyan and use
a ten to tell you for פרהסיא, parhesya, and in one case
it's defined by men and in one case it's not defined by
men, it's interesting that the same verse can be framed in different
ways. Okay, anyway, so now when you're dealing with the big three
are not about קידוש השם, kiddush Hashem, meaning עבודה זרה avodah zarah
might be about אהבת השם, ahavat Hashem, but that's different than קידוש
השם, kiddush Hashem, and the other things that are פרהסיא parhesya or
שעת השמד, sha'at hashmad, that's about קידוש השם. kiddush Hashem. Yes, Gloria.
I'm not sure why, I mean if the point is to show
that Judaism is being attacked and the Jews don't really care that
much about their religion, why is it relevant that it's in front
of ten Jews as opposed to, you know, a bunch of non-Jews?
Because you're not concerned what non-Jews think about it, you're concerned about
whether Jews are holding fast to the faith or not. What is
your act going to be saying to your fellow Jews? But it
would be saying the same thing if there's three Jews and 20,000
non-Jews. Oh, you mean if it's a real פרהסיא parhesya and then
the word gets around. Right, that's an interesting point. You know, I
guess the point is is that like, yeah, it's a good question,
you know, like you're saying like is the issue that if it's
among non-Jews the word won't spread and if it's among Jews the
word will spread? Or I think it's not just about the word
spreading. I think somehow it's like the power, I have to think
about that
more, but I think somehow it's like the power of the act.
Like if you're willing to
do this act in the middle of your Jewish community, somehow that's
just somehow more of a symbolically like you know it's like a
violation, I don't mean violation like a violation of a מצוה, mitzvah,
you know. If you do it among non-Jews, like you know what
happens in Vegas stays in Vegas. Like you know like we heard
that the guy did it but it somehow doesn't define us, you
know, in the same way. If something's happening in our midst, it
impacts our whole self-definition. I think there's a difference. I'd have to
think about it more but I don't think it's just about do
people find out. I think it's about the power of the act
in the moment. You know, if you think about the whole story
behind חנוכה, Chanukah, right, the guy is bringing the you know in
the in the you know in the מגילת חשמונאים, Megillat Chashmonaim, right,
the guy is bringing the you know, you know the story about
how חנוכה Chanukah starts, right? They're the Greeks are getting this Jew
to offer a sacrifice and and what's his name? What, with the
blemish on the animal? No, no, no, no, no. Ah, what's his
name? I can't believe I'm just blanking. יהודה Yehudah the המכבי's haMaccabi
father, יהודה, Yehudah, מתתיהו, Mattityahu, thank you, I can't believe I was
blanking on it. Anyway, so anyway, the story is right there in
the you know, is that he's in the book of חשמונאים Chashmonaim
that this guy is bringing a sacrifice and מתתיהו Mattityahu sees it
and it's right there amongst the Jewish community and it's being forced
to bring a sacrifice to עבודה זרה avodah zarah amongst, you know,
you know, whatever, by the, you know, by by the Greek. And
he sees it and he doesn't tolerate it and he intervenes and
he kills the guy and he says מי לה' אלי mi l'Hashem
elai and the people gather and that starts the whole revolt. You
know? So anyway, so that's exactly like you know this case, although
that's a case of using lethal force that just occurred to me
to stop an act of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, the whole thing
we were debating before. But anyway, I just think it's not just
about the word getting around. I think it's about the, I think
it's about like the power of the act when it occurs within
the community that you are trying to undermine their faith and you
did a public act in that community of violating a faith. I
think that that's like part of what it's about. Okay, let's just
read a little bit more. I know we're over, but I want
to just get at least a little bit more. Okay, and this
is, I mean it's a big topic but we'll just go do
it briefly. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, והא אסתר
פרהסיא הויא. v'ha Ester parhesya havaia. What do you mean? What do
you mean that פרהסיא parhesya you give up your life? אסתר Ester
was פרהסיא parhesya because אסתר Ester was, I mean the act of
intercourse didn't happen in the middle of the street, but everybody knew
about it. It was, you know, she was taken into the king's
palace. That's seen as happening בפרהסיא. b'parhesya. Okay, and she went along
with it, right? Why didn't she give up her life? Okay, so
אמר אביי אסתר קרקע עולם היתה. amar Abaye Ester karka olam hayeta.
She was just the ground. She was passive. So that's a, I'm
going to get back to that in a minute. Let's first read
רבא's Rava answer, which is an easier answer. רבא אמר הנאת עצמן
שאני. Rava amar hana'at atzman shani. When they're doing it, it's not
the big three and it's not a שעת השמד, sha'at hashmad, it's
just פרהסיא. parhesya. Then it depends. Is it פרהסיא parhesya but they're
really doing it out of self-interest? Then it's not an act that
then symbolically it's not an act of undermining a faith. If they're
doing it to make you transgress just for the purpose of making
you transgress, then it's an act of undermining a faith and demands
martyrdom. If they're doing it for their own pleasure, then that's not
what it's symbolically about. Then fine, it doesn't matter it's פרהסיא. parhesya.
Everybody understands. he wants me to bake bread for him, so I'm
going to bake bread for him so he doesn't kill me. Okay.
ואי לא תימא הכי, ve-ee lo teima hachi, if you don't say
that, הני כוואקי ודימוניקי, hani kavaki ve-dimuniki, those are certain types of
fire pans and apparently this is actually this was in the Zoroastrians
would have these fire rituals and they would demand that the Jews
contribute fire pans to their fire rituals. It was not considered עבודה
זרה avoda zara because the Jews weren't worshipping עבודה זרה. avoda zara.
They were only contributing vessels to be used, okay. So Rava says
היכי יהבינן להו, heichi yavina lehu, how do we give it to
them? Fine, it's not עבודה זרה, avoda zara, but it's very public
that we're contributing these things out of rather than getting killed, okay.
So why can we do it? It's פרהסיא. farhesya. אלא הנאת עצמן
שאני, ela hana'at atzman shani, when they're doing it for their own
הנאה. hana'ah. Interesting, here their own הנאה hana'ah is not physical pleasure,
their own הנאה hana'ah is their own worship of their god, but
it doesn't matter. It doesn't matter that they're doing it in worship
of their god. They're not doing it to make us violate, okay.
It's about their own self-interest. It's not to show that they can
make us transgress. So when that's what it's about, it's different and
even if it's in public, we transgress. So even if she was
Jewish, right? הכא נמי הנאת עצמן שאני, hacha nami hana'at atzman shani,
here too. Okay, so that's important. When do you do have to
give up your life, not the big three? Either it's a שעת
השמד, sha'at ha-shmad, right, so that they're really trying to undermine everything,
or it's an act in public done for the purpose of forcing
transgression. But an act in public done for the person's own self-interest,
then it doesn't matter, then you do not give up your life.
ואזל רבה לטעמיה, ve-azal Rava le-ta'ameih, because Rava goes according to his
reasoning. דאמר רבה, de-amar Rava, Rava says עכו"ם דאמר ליה להאי ישראל,
akum de-amar leh le-hai yisrael, if a non-Jew says to a Jew
קטול אספסתא בשבתא, ktol aspasta be-shabta, cut this type of a weed
on Shabbos ושדי לחיותא ve-shadi le-chayusa and give it to my animal
ואי לא קטלינא לך ve-ee lo katlina lach and if not I'll
kill you. So it's a little play on the word קטול ktol
which is to kill and קטול ktol which is to cut. So
לקטול ולא ליקטלוה, liktol ve-lo liktlo, let him cut the weed and
not get killed. Fine, being מחלל שבת בפרהסיא, mechallel shabbos be-farhesya, but
you're doing it because the Jew just wants his animals, the non-Jew
just wants his animals fed. But if he says שדי לנהרא, shadi
le-nahara, cut this weed or whatever this grass, this herb, and throw
it in the river, I'm not getting any benefit out of it.
I want to show that I can make you be מחלל שבת.
mechallel shabbos. If that's what he's saying, ליקטלוה ולא ליקטול, liktlo ve-lo
liktol, let him kill you and you don't cut the weed. Okay,
so it's a very nice play on words here, but yeah, it's
all about if he's trying to show he can make you transgress
or is he trying to actually just do it for his own
reason. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, why? לעבורי מילתא קא בעי, la'avorei milta
ka ba'ei, because he's just trying to make you transgress and therefore
that becomes an act of martyrdom. Okay, so we'll pause for here
for now but I want to say one thing because I skipped
over the whole thing of קרקע עולם. karka olam. And what the
heck does that mean that Esther's קרקע עולם? karka olam? Why does
that change it? First of all, what does that mean קרקע עולם?
karka olam? So for a number of ראשונים rishonim I should just
say, I can't unpack all of this, but I want to say
a few important things. For a number of ראשונים, rishonim, what it
means is that they just view that in the act of intercourse,
הלכה halacha always views the woman as passive and as having the
act of intercourse done to her, which is obviously strange that it
views that completely in those terms. But once it's viewing it in
those terms, so it's saying fine, the issue about יהרג ואל יעבור
yehareg ve-lo ya'avor is not to actively do an act of transgression.
But a passively, like תוספות tosafot says if somebody says let me
throw you on top of an infant and crush the infant's head
or if not I'll kill you, you can let the guy throw
you on the infant. You are not doing the act, the other
person is doing the act. So based on that, this is sort
of תוספות's tosafot approach. When we say יהרג ואל יעבור yehareg ve-lo
ya'avor by גילוי עריות, gilluy arayot, the גמרא, gemara, it's a question
of the גרסא girsa before. Was the גרסא girsa before יהרג ואל
יעבור yehareg ve-lo ya'avor by גילוי עריות? gilluy arayot? I mean excuse
me, יהרג ואל יעבור yehareg ve-lo ya'avor or was it תיהרג ואל
תעבור? tehareg ve-al ta'avor? The man should let himself be killed or
the woman should let herself be killed. Our גרסא girsa was תיהרג
ואל תעבור, tehareg ve-al ta'avor, she should let herself. But תוספות tosafot
says that's not the right גרסא. girsa. The גרסא girsa is the
man has to let himself be killed rather than transgress, but the
woman who halachically is deemed as passive. Now again, I'll say another
word about that, who halachically is deemed as passive, she can transgress
and not do it because it's really being done to her, she's
not doing it. Okay, so that's very so that's how תוספות, tosafot,
one very sort of way of understanding קרקע עולם. karka olam. And
then the point is that it's not only for the גילוי עריות
gilluy arayot perspective, that's even for this perspective of פרהסיא. farhesya. Okay,
even when it comes to the issue of קידוש השם, kiddush Hashem,
you might have thought if it's about the act of the עבירה
aveira itself, there's a distinction between being active and passive. Let's just
accept for a moment the idea that a woman is seen as
passive, okay, in the act of intercourse. So if it's about an
act of עבירה, aveira, fine, if I'm passive I can, I don't
have to give up my life. But if it's about קידוש השם,
Kiddush Hashem, if through me even not active, it creates a חילול
השם, chillul Hashem, right, it creates this desecration of God's name, then
maybe I have to give up my life even if I'm passive
because it's about the effect, the effect of קידוש השם, Kiddush Hashem,
the effect of חילול השם. chillul Hashem. And then he says no,
the answer in the גמרא Gemara אסתר קרקע עולם Esther karka olam
that even when it comes to an issue of קידוש השם, Kiddush
Hashem, even issues of פרהסיא, farhesya, if you're totally passive, it's okay.
So according to that read, you don't have to give up your
life for the big three or for קידוש השם Kiddush Hashem as
long as you're passive. It's only that you can't actively do something,
okay? But all of those assume that a woman is passive in
the act of intercourse. So what I want to say is, is
that it's possible that that's the גמרא Gemara is seeing that only
in the case of rape, right? Because in a case of rape,
right, it's not saying every act of intercourse a woman is passive.
In the case of rape a woman is passive, and the רמב"ן
Ramban even says further, in a case of rape, the reason we
could say, you know, that she has to she doesn't have to
give up her life is because like often even if she wanted
to give up her life rather than to be killed, she wouldn't
have that choice. So by when a woman is being raped we
don't say give up your life rather than commit the rape. Like
it's not the whole thing isn't in her hands. Okay, and in
that case yes, she is having the act perpetrated on her. She
is not actively doing it, okay? So that is true, okay? But
the problem with that is the Esther case, because Esther was not
there being raped by אחשוורוש, Achashveirosh, she was willingly participating. So then
he can, I mean, who knows what the how much choice the
women had? I understand, but I'm saying in the actual act, in
the bedroom, she wasn't just lying flat and letting something be done
to her, one doesn't imagine that, right? Okay, so to use the
idea of אסתר קרקע עולם, Esther karka olam, you know, to say
it's a funny idea to explain why she did this if there's
a פרהסיא farhesya problem and so on. Okay, so that's a really
interesting challenge in general about do we look at woman in general
as passive in the act of intercourse or only in a context
of when they're being, you know, raped? And then this idea of
of in the case of יהרג ואל יעבור yehareg v'al ya'avor by
עריות, arayos, does that equally apply to women, you know, by a
case of עריות, arayos, right, is a really important question which is
a major major debate in the ראשונים. Rishonim. All right, so we
will end with this, שתהא גמר חתימה טובה she-tehei gmar chasima tova
and what I think I'm going to do is the following is
I'll try to find some time today, I might find some time.